Welcome, my name is Martin Keene and I'm delighted to be your instructor as we explore how open
standards are implemented in a ZOS system by ZOS Unix.
We're going to be looking at all aspects from this, from the far system to the shell and
beyond, and you'll get your chance to get your hands dirty with a series of lab exercises
using a real IBM Z Unix system.
To try out the concepts that we will be covering here.
So let's get cracking.
Now, ZOS Unix brings together the open world and the ZOS world.
Both worlds can coexist independently while sharing the same processing and storage resources.
And it's a case of getting the best of both worlds, a standard interface and portability
from the open part of ZOS Unix and a larger rate of services from the MVS part of ZOS.
ZOS Unix supports an environment of large operating systems or servers, distributed systems and
workstations that share common interfaces.
ZOS Unix supports the set of standards being developed by the open group.
This includes the portable operating system interface better known as POSIX.
Users can concentrate their work in the environment where they're most comfortable, be that Unix
or be that MVS.
So for example, application developers can develop most of their applications at their
workstations and then use standard POSIX interfaces to compile, test and debug their
programs on the ZOS system.
Current ZOS applications run as usual.
Current users continue to have all of the services of ZOS available.
And with ZOS Unix, the existing investment in ZOS applications and data is protected.
New applications will have access to existing data.
Now, what are open systems?
Well, based on requirements from customers, the characteristics of an open system environment
can be expressed by the following elements.
First off, there's portability.
This is the ability to relocate system resources such as applications, data and people between
processing environments of different design and different architectures.
There's also interoperability.
This defines the ability to interconnect systems from different vendors and have them work
together to solve a business problem.
And finally, there's investment protection, which is the ability to choose components
from offerings of many vendors, many protocols and many architectures, all with the confidence
that they're going to work together.
In an open system environment, a set of standards can provide the ability to interoperate and
to port applications, data and people on different operating platforms.
Now, the vendor names that we're showing here, they're just an example.
But the point is, it's this defined set of standards in the middle that enable interoperability
and portability of applications.
And there are two types of standards.
There are de facto standards and de jure standards.
De facto standards, those are established by broad industry usage of a technology.
And de jure standards are established and accepted by recognized standard bodies through a formal
voting process.
The single Unix specification or SUS is the collective name of a family of standards for
computer operating systems, compliance with which is required to qualify for using the
Unix trademark.
If an operating system is submitted to the open group for certification and passes conformance
tests, then it's deemed to be a compliant Unix standard.
ZOS Unix meets these open systems requirements.
Unix applications which conform to XPG 4.2 standards can be ported to ZOS.
These can be vendor applications or self-developed applications.
Now does this mean that every Unix application should run on Z?
Well of course not, but applications that require true enterprise server qualities
of service, they are well suited.
If your application has high DASD requirements, high security needs, or needs a high level
of reliability, then you'll see a lot of benefit in moving that application to ZOS
Unix.
In the next video, we'll take a look at how Unix is implemented with ZOS.